Documenting Lesbian Lives Oral History Project oral histories SSC.MS.00661
Sophia Smith Collection
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2011; 2.5 linear feet (2 full letter document boxes, 1 half letter document box, 2 medium card boxes); 43 Gigabytes (83 digital video and text files)
  - Laura Sullivan interviewed by Melissa Yvette Pena, 2011 April 7; Sullivan, Laura; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    In this oral history, Laura Sullivan begins by describing her childhood in a close-knit Italian-American family, where the listener gains insight into her privileged upbringing. Her loving and supportive family provided a disciplined and structured foundation, where she had strong female role models (i.e. a mother who was a nurse and a grandmother who owned a bakery), which helped lead her to a life filled with self-determination and confidence.
    The interview mainly focuses on Laura Sullivan's interest, entrance, and existence within the BDSM community, beginning with her involvement in "shoe-licking" shenanigans in the second grade, to opening the Chateau, a mass BDSM club, to her commitment to her present, private BDSM club in Connecticut. Through her personal reflections, the audience is allowed access to the emotional and literal negotiations between the roles of wife, mother, daughter, teacher, student, etc., through a perceived sexualized lens. Her story offers valuable information on the study of alternative sexualities and women entrepreneurs in the sex industry, as well as providing a normalized perspective of what is often considered a taboo subject.
    Sullivan, Laura
    - Video interview of Laura Sullivan
    - Transcript of interview of Laura Sullivan (Box 3)
  - Kate Wolfe interviewed by Annie-Sage Whitehurst, 2011 April 9; Wolfe, Kate; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Kate Wolfe (b. 1964) grew up in El Paso, Texas, with her mother, step-father and one of two older brothers. She graduated from the University of Texas at El Paso in 1986, and stayed at the university to earn her MA in Experimental Psychology in 1989. In 1994, Wolfe earned her Ph.D in Social Psychology from the University of Houston. Wolfe's subsequent employment includes pre- and post-doctoral positions as a teaching assistant, a research fellow, a director of research projects and, in 2001 she began teaching at community colleges in Washington, Connecticut, Illinois, Texas, Oregon and Massachusetts. Her published work includes articles in the Journal of Clinical Psychology (1990), Journal of Psychoactive Drugs (1995), and the American Journal of Public Health (1996). (All articles published under her previous name, Susanna M. Perry). Wolfe currently holds four teaching positions (virtual and physical) as a Tenured Psychology Instructor at Seattle Central Community College, an Adjunct Psychology Instructor at Springfield Technical Community College, Asnuntuck Community College and Holyoke Community College.
    Wolfe grew up in a white, working-class Catholic household and moved frequently as her step-father, a former sailor in the Navy and her mother, a registered nurse diagnosed with Lupus, looked for work throughout Texas and New Jersey. Wolfe lived with her parents until 1989 when she moved to Houston, where she came out as a lesbian and began the first of three significant relationships. Wolfe lived in Seattle, Portland and California before moving to Massachusetts with her current girlfriend Kellye Rowland ('AC) in 2010.
    In this oral history Kate Wolfe describes her childhood in Texas, her estranged relationship with her stepfather and elder siblings and the year spent sleeping in a car while her parents moved the family across the country in search of work. The interview focuses on Wolfe's romantic, intellectual and emotional life since grade school, her employment history and her lesbian identity. Wolfe's story illuminates the experiences of working-class lesbians, perspectives on the "queer" label, Wolfe's marriage in 2003 to then-girlfriend in Portland, her attempts to reconnect/ distance herself from her family and her activities in academia.
    Wolfe, Kate
    - Video interview of Kate Wolfe
    - Transcript of interview of Kate Wolfe (Box 3)
  - Original tapes, and preservation master DVD's, 2011 (Box 4, Box 5)
- Documenting Lesbian Lives, 2012; 30 Gigabytes (75 digital video and text files)
  - Mare Chapman interviewed by Sophie Steinberger, 2012 March 16 and 19; Chapman, Mare; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Mare Chapman (b. 1944) grew up near Kalamazoo, MI. She graduated from Wayne State University in Detroit with a degree in Occupational Therapy and later earned her masters degree in counseling psychology. Chapman has taught classes in psychiatric O.T. at Wayne State University and University of Wisconsin Madison and has worked in the public mental health system in a variety of capacities, including as the director of a community program for mentally ill adults. She currently is in private practice and a teacher of mindfulness meditation in Madison, WI.
    In this oral history Mare Chapman describes growing up as a tomboyish child in her educated, emotion-hiding "fine family" as well as her Michigan country high school. The interview follows her feminist awakening, growth and motivation parallel to her career and to her progression through high school dating, marriage to a man, introductory lesbian dalliances, and long-term lesbian partnerships. Chapman's story depicts her experience as a mother and wife in "traditional" heterosexual marriage and it's lack of cohesion, equality, and fulfillment before her personal awakening and transition into a woman-centered life. Chapman expresses the joy and fulfillment she has found through other women, family, her career, and meditation practice.
    Chapman, Mare
    - Video interview of Mare Chapman
    - Transcript of interview of Mare Chapman (Box 1)
  - Carla Cooke interviewed by Allie Bernard, 2012 April 15; Cooke, Carla; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Cooke, Carla
    - Video interview of Carla Cooke
      Closed without express narrator permission until April 15, 2042.
    - Transcript of interview of Carla Cooke (Box 3)
  - Kate Davenport interviewed by Karla Faber, 2012 April 6; Davenport, Kate; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Kathryn (Kate) Davenport was born in Gloucester, Massachusetts in 1957. She spent her childhood growing up in Massachusetts, Maine and New Hampshire. Davenport moved to Boston at the age of 18 to attend a secretarial school. After living in Boston for a while, Davenport attended the University of Massachusetts and soon after, attended the Smith School of Social Work. After earning her degree she worked as a social worker and a therapist. While at Smith she married and had one daughter. She divorced her husband at the age of 35 and simultaneously came out, when she met her first partner. Davenport's passions lie in being a parent, and finding tools like yoga, and meditation to be the best person she can be. She lives with her partner of ten years, and currently works as a private psychotherapist.
    In this oral history Kate Davenport discusses her unstable childhood, and moving to Boston by herself at a young age. She talks about her time at UMass and at the Smith School of Social Work and the challenge of finding herself throughout her adolescence and adulthood. The importance of parenting is highlighted throughout the interview, as well as her exploration of tools, like yoga and therapy, she utilized to overcome the abuse and neglect of her childhood, to bring her to her current point in life.
    Davenport, Kate
    - Video interview of Kate Davenport
    - Transcript of interview of Kate Davenport (Box 1)
  - BJ Entwisle interviewed by Lillie Scheffey, 2012 April 5; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    This interview is closed until January 1, 2032. No bio or abstract online. No online access.
    - Video interview of BJ Entwisle
    - Transcript of interview of BJ Entwisle (Box 3)
      Closed until January 1, 2032.
  - Judith Evans interviewed by Jennifer Krain, 2012 March 23; Evans, Judith; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Judith Evans (b. 1940) was born in Wareham, Massachusetts where she lived during her early childhood. At age 12 Evans' family relocated to Harrisburg, Pennsylvania where she lived for most of her adult life. Evans graduated from High School and went on to secretarial school where she learned the appropriate skills needed for an office job. Evans worked for Equitable Insurance for 13 years before working at the State Hospital for 26 years as an aid. During her time at the State Hospital she also served as a nurse for the 316th Medical Unit of the Army Reserves. She served a term of two years. Currently Evans resides in Villas, New Jersey living a happy retired life. In New Jersey Evans has volunteered at both a local animal shelter and women's abuse center.
    In this oral history Judith Evans describes her childhood, careers, and romantic relationships during her lifetime. Evans discusses the hardships of growing up with an unsupportive parent and the stress created from living a double life. Evans also focuses on the stress felt at work and the need to be closeted for fear of being fired. Evans has always taken a caregiver role, volunteering for several years at an animal shelter and women's abuse center. Evans' discusses her motives not to join any feminist movements during the 1970's and 1980's because of the lesbian feminist reputation for being far left. She also comments on the ability to "pass" on the streets because of her feminine looks. Her story contrasts that of separatist feminist feelings as Evans promotes having friends of both sexes and sexuality. Her story also comments on a life experienced with different partners and the challenges of being in a committed relationship.
    Evans, Judith
    - Video interview of Judith Evans
    - Transcript of interview of Judith Evans (Box 1)
  - Janet Harris interviewed by Taylor Schulte, 2012 March 30; Harris, Janet; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Harris, Janet
    - Video interview of Janet Harris
    - Transcript of interview of Janet Harris (Box 3)
  - Deborah Heller interviewed by Kayla Ginsburg, 2012 April 7 and 8; Heller, Deborah; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Deborah Heller (born August 19, 1940) was raised in Brooklyn, New York in an upwardly mobile Jewish family. She graduated from Smith in 1961 as a sociology major and then proceeded to attend the School of Social Work for one year, which ended her up in Cleveland where she met her husband. After 10 years of marriage, she divorced her husband and came out as a lesbian in the 1970s. She earned a masters and a doctorate at Boston College between 1972 and 1976. She taught at Goddard in an adult degree program, BC as a teaching fellow, and started a gender identity clinic. Instead of pursuing academia, she became head of counseling and women's services at a women's health clinic, and then director of ambulatory services for department of psychiatry at Cambridge Hospital, with an appointment at the medical school. Then in 1982, she started HellerCunningham, a consulting firm helping organizations (profit and non-profit) become more successful. Heller has been active her whole life. She was involved in anti-Vietnam organizing, early reproductive and abortion rights, and the women's movement. She was a Board member of Fenway Community Health Service. She and her partner Ann Sanders started the Fenway Women's Dance, one of the first major women's dances, together over 20 years ago. She has been with her current partner, Ann for 26 years. They were legally married in 2004 in Massachusetts. They currently live in Provincetown, Massachusetts.
    In this oral history, Deborah Heller discusses her childhood in Brooklyn, New York and her transition to Smith College. She describes Smith in the late 1950s and goes on to talk about her decision to go to the Smith School of Social Work. She discusses her time in Puerto Rico in the Peace Corps and her work in Boston before divorcing her husband. She talks about her academic interest in gender and sexuality in graduate school occurring before and simultaneous to her coming out. She focuses on the women's movement through lesbian feminism and often discussing lesbian community in Boston. She discusses her political work, including teaching workshops on lesbian sexuality at the short-lived lesbian college, Sagaris. She comments on her experiences during the AIDS crisis and work on the board of Fenway, as well as starting the Fenway Women's Dance with her partner, Ann Sanders. The interview focuses on her political work, as well as her personal life.
    Heller, Deborah
    - Video interview of Deborah Heller
    - Transcript of interview of Deborah Heller (Box 1)
  - Joan Laird interviewed by Erin Hopkins, 2012 April 13; Laird, Joan; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Joan Laird (b. 1934) grew up in Rochester, New York, graduated with a BA in political science from Vassar, and a MSW from Columbia. She taught at Eastern Michigan University's Social Work Program. She did three-years of postdoctoral work in anthropology and social work at the University of Michigan. She co-founded the Ann Arbor Center for the Family with her partner, Ann Hartman. Her partner Ann Hartman was dean of the Smith School for Social Work. She has published several books with Hartman on the topic of family therapy. Laird has also taught at Smith, and has been a pioneer in researching and working with lesbians in the field of social work.
    This oral history details Joan Laird's evolving relationships with her family. Laird's marriage with her ex-husband, the birth of her son, Duncan, and her relationship with her current partner, Ann Hartman, is discussed.Her experiences at Vassar in the fifties are described as well. The interview includes stories of Laird's time in Ann Arbor as a postdoctoral student in social work and anthropology as well as the opening of the Ann Arbor Center for Family with Hartman. Laird talks about the coming-out process in numerous contexts and the particular struggles of doing so in the field of social work. She also describes her work with gay and lesbian families in the field of social work. She also reflects on the evolving environment for queer people.
    Laird, Joan
    - Video interview of Joan Laird
    - Transcript of interview of Joan Laird (Box 1)
  - Janet Lathrop interviewed by Hannah Pepin, 2012 April 8; Lathrop, Janet; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Janet Lathrop (b. 1951) grew up in Madison, Wisconsin with her mother, father, and one younger brother. She holds a B.A. degree in journalism and a M.S. in science communication from University of Wisconsin, Madison. She identifies as a lesbian and a writer and has worked for a variety of organizations and publications as a newspaper reporter, editor, and science writer. She continued to travel and write until 2008, when she came to the UMass Amherst News Office as the campus science writer. Jan's first relationship was with a woman, from 1964-68, but she resisted the label of "lesbian" and eventual married a man, Mike Downs, in 1971. She had once child with him, a son named Paul, but eventually divorced her husband in 1987. Since then she has been in two partnerships with women, including one lasting 16 years from 1991 to 2007. She now lives Massachusetts with her parakeet, Phoebe, and is not currently married or partnered.
    In this oral history Janet Lathrop describes growing up in Wisconsin in a small, upwardly mobile family, and her journey through college and beyond. This interview traces the development of Lathrop's early sexual and romantic attraction to women over men, and her struggle within a family that often felt constricting and even fearful of her preferences. Lathrop describes her high school and college years, including her involvement in anti-war activism on campus in Madison, Wisconsin. Never quite identifying with the word "lesbian" or the other lesbians she met, Lathrop talks about her decision to marry a man and about becoming increasingly unhappy in her marriage as the years went on. The interview also touches on Lathrop's development as a writer, and her involvement in a number of newspapers and other publications. Lathrop speaks to the experience of coming out late in life, of parenting as a lesbian, and especially to the discovery of a supportive and welcoming lesbian community and its importance in her life.
    Lathrop, Janet
    - Video interview of Janet Lathrop
    - Transcript of interview of Janet Lathrop (Box 1)
  - Eileen Myles interviewed by Brittni Hayes, 2012 March 30; Myles, Eileen; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Eileen Myles (b. 1949) grew up in Arlington, Massachusetts, attended Catholic school, and graduated from the University of Massachusetts- Boston, with a BA in English. She moved to New York in 1974 to become a poet and since then has received multiple awards and grants for her work. In 1991, Myles ran for President of the United States of America, leading the first all-female write-in campaign. She served as a Professor Emeritus at the University of California at San Diego from 2002-2007. Myles currently lives in New York with her partner of three years, Leopoldine.
    In this oral history, Eileen Myles describes the complexities of existing as a queer, working class individual. She details her childhood spent in the suburbs of Boston attending Catholic schools and reflects on the presence of Nuns in her early life. The interview, however, focuses more specifically on the later years of her life, following her move to New York City in 1974 with aspirations of becoming a poet. Myles details her experiences in the poetry scene of the lower east side, specifically her time at Saint Mark's Church, and speaks of her coming out process as being inherently tied to the poetry community. Myles speaks heavily about the activist sentiment present in her work, as she feels her work relates to the larger political spheres of feminism and queer politics. Myles' story brings awareness to the intersectional aspects of identity (in this case, sexuality and class). Additionally, she sheds light on the way in which activism at a communal level can be isolating, while simultaneously remaining imperative at a personal level. Myles traces this thought through her relationship with second wave feminism and the political environment of the 90s. This oral history provides excellent insight into personal, queer interaction with the larger political and cultural spheres from the 1970s-present day.
    Myles, Eileen
    - Video interview of Eileen Myles
    - Transcript of interview of Eileen Myles (Box 2)
  - Kristi Nelson interviewed by Elizabeth Weissert, 2012 April 3; Nelson, Kristi; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Kristi Nelson (b.1960) was born in Yonkers, NY to young parents who were in college. She is the oldest of three siblings. She has a brother (b.1961) and a sister (b.1963). After moving around frequently, her family settled in Amherst, MA where her father became an English professor. When she was 17 years old, her parents divorced and her mother moved to Connecticut to pursue a career in law. After taking a few years off to work and travel, Nelson enrolled in UMass Amherst and declared a major in Women's Studies. In 1983 Nelson got married and dropped out of college. She was married for four years and got divorced in 1987. Nelson began a career in fundraising and philanthropy working for the Peace Development Fund, the Progressive Group, 20/20 Vision, and Food & Water inc.
    In 1992 Nelson was diagnosed with stage four lymphoma. After an intense struggle with cancer, Nelson began working for hospice. In 1997 Nelson was hired as Executive Director of the Women's Fund of Western Massachusetts. In 2002 she finished her B.A. in Women's Studies from UMass Amherst. She went on to complete the Leadership for Change program at Boston College in 2003. She ran her own fundraising company for non-profit organizations called Inside Out from 2002 to 2006. In 2007 she completed a Masters in Public Administration at Harvard University. She worked at Kripalu Center for Yoga and Health from 2007 to 2008.
    Nelson currently works at the Center for Mindfulness in Medicine, Health Care and Society in Worcester, MA. She lives in Hadley, MA with her partner Linda and Linda's two children from a previous marriage.
    In this oral history Kristi Nelson describes her experience as a social activist throughout her life and the many forms her activism has taken. The interview follows the course of Nelson's life from her experiences as the child of activist parents to her current role in non-profit fundraising. Nelson's story encompasses her more radical social activism in high school and college. She reflects on the feminist and lesbian separatist movements in the early 1980's, focusing on her experience as a bisexual woman. Nelson's story then moves to her career in fundraising for non-profit organizations and the way this fundraising connects with her social activism. Nelson relates her experience as a cancer survivor and the way this experience shaped her spirituality. She describes her philosophy as a mindfulness practitioner. She reflects on homophobia within the women's movement and describes her experience of being closeted within the movement. Nelson's story includes her experience of being a lesbian mother in a non-traditional family. Finally Nelson reflects on the current state of the gay rights movement, social activism and American politics.
    Nelson, Kristi
    - Video interview of Kristi Nelson
    - Transcript of interview of Kristi Nelson (Box 2)
  - Roberta Pato interviewed by Vivian Andreani, 2012 April 14; Pato, Roberta; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Roberta Pato (b. 1946) was born in the Bronx and was raised in the Lower East Side in New York City. She spent most of her life in NYC, and attended Hunter College, an all-women's college in Manhattan. She also earned an MS in Education, and taught in the NYC Public School system from 1967 to 1990 — when she moved to Arlington, Massachusetts for three years and worked as an accounts clerk at MIT — resuming in 1993 and working until her retirement in 2002. She currently resides in Northampton, and is actively involved in LGBT and anti-violence organizing in the Valley.
    In this oral history, Roberta Pato describes growing up Jewish in a multi-cultural apartment building in New York City, her early consciousness of lesbian desire and the pressure towards conformity. Pato contrasts the differences between her experiences with men and women, and the process of finding relationships. She details the painful experience of losing the love she found with a woman to societal expectations. Pato discusses the experience of being married to a man for nine years, and the affair and a thirty four year partnership with an abusive woman. The interview focuses on the process of losing family due to this relationship, and reconnecting to them, the reality and consequences of an abusive partnership, the arduous process of leaving an abuser, the finding of a lesbian community and searching for love and company in more recent years. Pato emphasizes the importance of safety and truthfulness, and the toll taken from being at least partially closeted for almost thirty four years.
    Pato, Roberta
    - Video interview of Roberta Pato
    - Transcript of interview of Roberta Pato (Box 2)
  - Carmen Quinones interviewed by Elise Smith, 2012 March 19; Quinones, Carmen; 1 oral histories (transcript and video)
    Quinones, Carmen
    - Video interview of Carmen Quinones